Guide to the Department of Physiology, Office Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1961-1982 UA.90.36.6.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Department of Physiology, Office Files, University of Pittsburgh
1961-1982
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Department of Physiology
UA.90.36.6.10
1 Linear Feet (one box and one oversize drawing)
This collection contains University of Pittsburgh Department of Physiology staff meeting minutes from 1961 to 1981 and documents the development of the program while it was led by Dr. Ernst Knobil.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Julane Knobil to the Health Sciences Library. Transferred to the University Archives on March 14, 2016.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of Physiology Department staff meeting minutes and photographs belonged to the R.B. Mellon Chair of Physiology, Dr. Ernst Knobil. Spanning from 1961 to 1981, his entire time as the founding chair, these minutes and articles from university publications document the progress of the department as it developed into one of the nation's best physiology programs.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biography
In 1961, Dean Francis Cheever hired Dr. Ernst Knobil to lead the newly established Physiology Department, which was to be separated from the Pharmacology Department. Dr. Knobil left Harvard to become the first Richard Beatty Mellon endowed chair of physiology at the University of Pittsburgh. He developed the department from scratch using a grant of more than one million dollars from the R.K. Mellon Foundation and focused the department's research on his area of study, endocrine physiology, to distinguish it from other programs over the course of twenty years. Dr. Knobil left the University of Pittsburgh in 1981 to become Dean of the University of Texas Medical School in Houston.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Physiology; Knobil, Ernst
- Department Staff Photographs, 1962-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Staff Meeting Minutes, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Dr. Ernst Knobil Articles in University Publications (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Colloquia and News Clippings, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Drawing: Proposed Plum Borough Facility, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine (Oversize 1)